software engineering radio episode 77
fault tolerance with Bob hammer
part one
[Music]
welcome listeners to another episode of
su radio this episode is the first of a
two-part series about fault tolerance
it's an interview with Bob hammer bob
has been working in the telecoms
business with Alcatel Lucent for well a
bunch of years and he has been writing
patterns about fault tolerance for a
number of years at various plopp
conferences recently actually in
November more or less right now he has
been publishing a book on fault
tolerance patterns in Wiley software
pattern series and the episode we're
doing here is based on his book I think
it's really really great stuff in here
and everybody should listen to this kind
of stuff because it really helps to make
systems more available more reliable and
obviously more fault tolerant this is as
I said a two-part episode this is the
first episode in ten days we'll have the
second episode have fun so Bob welcome
to the show I thank you very much
so why don't we start by you introducing
yourself a little bit so our listeners
know who they're talking to okay or
listening to I should say I'm Bob hanmer
I'm with Alcatel Lucent used to be with
Lucent Technologies and before that Bell
Laboratories the name keeps changing the
work is the same and for a number of
years I've been active in the pattern
community usually participating in the
North America pattern conference and
I've been working for a number of years
within the area of telecommunications
and in particular switching systems and
other systems that are highly available
so we always want our telephone calls to
work and so that's what led me down this
Avenue when I was deciding we're working
on patterns this was the area that I
seemed to be working in the most and
seemed like a fruitful way to do it okay
so that's let's get into the topic I
think there is one underlying assumption
basically underlying all these fault
tolerance
discussions and that's the the
assumption of an imperfect world I guess
so things can't fail right yes things
fail all the time you go to the ATM and
it decides it doesn't want to dispense
any money or the telephone call in the
US we get a fast busy signal if all
circuits are busy
so lots of things that are controlled by
computers are failing all the time and
you mentioned already a couple of
typical application areas where failures
are part of the well part of the normal
case you mentioned telecommunication
systems are there other systems that are
well where it's important that a failure
is handled in a controlled manner I
should maybe say well that gets to a
question of philosophy and my philosophy
is that yes everything should handle
their failures and their faults and
their errors nicely so the user doesn't
get bothered by them unfortunately many
suppliers of commercial software for PCs
just assume that the users will stop
complaining after a while and so they
don't need to worry about the failures
and will stop complaining and will find
workarounds yeah but so I think any
really any domain in particular you know
enterprise-grade systems real-time
systems like you mentioned those are
really prime areas for this let's stop
by discussing some of the important
terms in the our area of fault-tolerant
systems so one of the terms probably is
is the term fault since it's part of the
name so a fault is the basic defect so
it's the misplaced comma or the design
that didn't capture something correctly
or the you know coding backwards that
kind of thing so the fault is the actual
defect sometimes people would call it a
bug I try to avoid that because I've
been in many situations where actually
talking about what was the fault and
what was the error and what was the
failure has been really useful and if we
just said the bug it wouldn't have given
us the information to help debug the
problem yeah so but you do say debugging
and not defaulting
that's true you're right okay just
joking
um you mentioned these other terms error
and failure what what's the difference
to default right so let's jump to
failure so the failure is actually the
the observed deviation from the
requirements or the specification and if
there aren't requirements or
specification then you can't have a
failure so but so the failure is like
what the user perceives as being the
problem or someone has to see that it
doesn't conform to the specification
mm-hm
the error is the incorrect state caused
by the fault that can lead to the
failure so the error is something in the
middle it's a real state it's of the
system it's not just a you know a
transition so there is there are errors
that are in the system but they haven't
caused the externally visible failure
yet mm-hm can you maybe give us an
example where these three terms become
clear to listeners well let me give you
a couple examples because some people
work better going forward and some
people work better up grasping the
concepts backwards so for the example
starting with a fault imagine like a
robotic arm that's gonna drill some part
and there's a misplaced decimal point or
decimal comma yeah and in a constant
well and so that's the fault and then
the error is that that constant gets
used to compute the number of steps that
the stepper motor on the robot should
take but because of the constant it
computes the in incorrect number of
steps that's the error and then when the
arm actually moves that amount it
becomes the externally visible failure
and so we've got the fault which is the
cut the misplaced comma we have the
error which was the incorrect
computation and then we have the failure
which was the incorrect motion okay you
know going the other way you know you
get that telephone bill and it's got the
wrong amount on it you know and that's
the failure the error is that there are
some charges on it that weren't you
and that became you know the failure
when you noticed it and the fault might
have been that an incorrect line
identification was used when creating
the billing record mm-hmm so failures
are always the things that are perceived
by the well by the user or by the
environment of the system yes so that's
ultimately what annoys people yes okay
so there are other terms that I would
typically associate with fault tolerance
one is that you need to be fault
tolerant if you're in a reliable or
highly available system so there are
those terms reliability availability
dependability how do these relate to to
fault tolerance and arrows and faults
well so fault huh when I say
fault-tolerant systems or fault
tolerance I'm really talking about
software and systems that are designed
to tolerate faults to continue operation
reliability and availability are the way
we measure how effectively that works
and reliability is strictly speaking
it's the probability that the system
will perform its desired functionality
for a specified period of time so like a
space shuttle mission has a specified
period of time that it's going to be in
space and it has to perform with very
high reliability for that time no
availability is a little bit different
concept and a lot of people get them
confused availability is the percentage
of the time or the proportion of the
time that the system is available to
perform work reliability talks about for
a finite duration availability talks
over you know over forever what
percentage of time is available now so
you want things you want things like the
Space Shuttle to be highly reliable you
want things like the telephone network
to be highly available because you
always want to be able to make a
telephone call now see the difference
and then there's some things where you
really want both like the ATM network
automatic teller machines you know you
always want to be able to get cash but
you always the bank at least always
wants the correct amount to be dispensed
so both it has to for that duration of
that transaction has to really be
correct
and reliable and but it has to be
available for service and then combining
the two and really needing the both and
needing other aspects like security and
safety gets to the definition of
dependability that dependability is a
bigger concept and then reliability
availability security and safety are
kind of sub concepts so dependability is
basically what what people perceive
again as the system doing a good job and
doing what the system should do yes okay
is there any specific relationship to
performance I mean you said that the
system has to perform correctly or or is
performance in that context also
something we talked about like deadlines
and transactions per minute and
something right it's well it's both
really that performance we're both
talking about meeting all the deadlines
and you're failing to meet the deadlines
that's an error or it could be a failure
so that performance in that sense we're
also if if you're making a system that's
you know really low performance you only
you're going to work with one
transaction of a minute that kind of
thing you're probably not going to spend
the time making it fault tolerant so you
know there's some correlation there but
then there's another part the
specifications for the system and the
software should identify how the system
is going to behave under various
workloads you know which is the
performance of the system and so it's
possible to have a performance error
such as an overload you know that's a
fault and in the sense that the system
is receiving more work than it can
handle and so as a result fault
tolerance can address that kind of
performance error okay so I think we're
not at the at the the place where we can
actually define what fault tolerance is
right I mean we discussed all the
building blocks so so what is what is
fault tolerance fault tolerance refers
to designing a system or the software
for a system and you'll find that I kind
of use the words interchangeably because
we're talking about bigger pieces of
software not just
you know one program yeah but so so what
fault tolerance is talking about
software systems that are designed to
automatically detect and correctly
process faults and errors to keep them
from becoming failures mm-hmm so the
goal is to you know stop failures and we
do that by detecting and isolating and
processing faults or errors as whatever
we detect to allow the system to
continue operation okay so as I guess
the it's not just relevant for for well
to keep our listeners listening I mean
also those who don't build telecom
systems or build software from space
shuttles I guess it's important to have
well - if you want to build any kind of
reasonable system that having then
having fault tolerance concepts in the
back of your mind is probably useful
even if they might not be the primary
concern right I agree so so can you talk
a little bit about the the fault
tolerant mindset what is important to
keep in the in the back of your mind if
if you want to build systems that have
these dependability characteristics
right so fault tolerant mindset is a
phrase that we started using just talk
about always wondering you know what can
go wrong here it's always thinking as
you're designing something or as you're
trying to debug something you know what
could go wrong here why how could it go
wrong and continually asking that
question and that is what I refer to as
the fault tolerant mindset but it's
really you know it's a frame of thought
that you're always going to be worried
about something failing and so you've
got you're going to design in the
correct techniques to handle that when
it does happen so there are probably a
couple of specific design trade-offs you
have to you have to make if you want to
have a fault tolerant program I guess
right it's definitely going to be more
expensive to develop a fault tolerant
piece of software and it's also going to
probably take a little bit more code
although one of the big principles
fault-tolerant design is to keep it
simple because every line of code you
add might you know or every class you
add or every whatever could hide other
faults and so you really want efficient
streamlined code that does what you need
to without a lot of extra bells and
whistles because they may be harboring
the fault so the trade offs and then I
don't want to over emphasize that it's
going to cost you know a lot more always
but especially if the designers have a
fault-tolerant mindset people sometimes
are I could well we could argue that a
good system that has high internal
quality is more or less automatically
fault tolerant is that correct is fault
tolerant just simply bug free or is
there more to it this Marcus is one of
my soapbox is unfortunately okay or so
this is a I agree it's a really common
in my opinion misconception software
quality is concerned with how well the
software is designed and built our good
methods used like code inspections and
design inspections and is there
repository for things you know so with
that people can find the design document
when they have to go back and refer to
it that kind of stuff that's quality and
so it's a quality talks about how you
build the system fault tolerance on the
other hand is talking about what you put
into the system so the techniques that
I've written about in my book they're
all things that are being designed into
the system or the last chapter is a
little bit crosses this boundary but
most of them are things that are
designed into the system that allow the
system to behave in a certain way that
makes it fault tolerant and so I say
quality is about the art of making the
software and fault tolerance is about
the software itself and what it what it
does okay so another thing you already
mentioned is that the simple of the
system is the less are the fewer chances
there are for faults because the simpler
the less stuff the less faults I guess
there are more
things to it for example um there are
certainly some features of certain
languages that are more susceptible to
being faulty for example pointers
so I guess defensive programming or
whatever you'd like to call this is also
something that's very useful yes and
indeed it's the defense of programming
or the thing the little things that
people learn slowly over in school that
relate to how you design your code to be
take care of itself or not have faults
and so you're you know careful with
pointers you're careful with memory
designing data structures in certain
ways such as two-way linked lists
instead of single a list a linked list
allow you to recreate things and figure
out what's going on better so there are
a lot of things like that you know
coding standards is another example a
lot of the defensive programming things
are at the coding level there are things
that you do when you're when you're
coding you keep in the back of your mind
and again what I put in my book are the
higher level design and architectural
concepts yeah that you can put on top
and then use the defensive programming
as you actually implement them but it's
the higher level things that are going
to give you know the larger system
better fault tolerance so one of these
things has probably even also end
version programming that you have
several versions of the same thing that
don't fail because of the same faults I
think that's hopefully correct
terminology right that's a technique
that's discussed a lot in the in the
literature it's one that I didn't really
include in my book because in version
programming for to really be on version
programming and really be effective
requires completely different design
teams and design environments working
off the same specification and and
that's just impractical for a lot of
things unless you know it's a project
like the Space Shuttle with a large
budget and reliability is extremely
extremely extremely important yeah I
heard about or I listened to a guy once
who talked about software for Airbus
flight controllers and he said they have
several different processor platforms
and also one team did it in Ada the
other team did it in C or C++ so that's
probably an example
of that case of an aversion programming
that's perfect example of it yes so so
before we get to to the pattern stuff
what's the role of formal verification
in all that is it is it practical and
well is it useful in in practice to to
actually verify a program formally and
and say something about its well its
quality and/or its level of fault
tolerance
yes it's I think it's very important I
mean putting this stuff into the code to
make it fault tolerant or you know
putting it into the design to make it
fault tolerant doesn't mean that you
know all the simple misplaced commas and
periods are out of the way so
verification is very important and
verification
you know rigorous verification can also
give you an idea about whether you're
going to achieve your availability and
reliability requirements and also
through the use of techniques such as
software reliability engineering
techniques such as reliability growth
modeling you can actually use the
results of your testing to get an idea
of whether you're getting the last few
defects out and so verification is very
important this you know the whole point
of being fault tolerant again it's
something about happens in execution
time in the system and so you want to
verify it during design time and and and
this verification is it more manual
manual review kind of stuff or is it
automatic automatic based on tools
typically well I would say it would be
the whole gamut of you know whatever the
the project usually does in terms of
quality it is what you need to continue
just because you're putting it into the
code doesn't mean you shouldn't you know
design it with high quality and I think
that verification is there's an element
of that but one of the things that can
be done during verification is through
kind of comprehensive testing and you
have to really plan the testing well and
in insert defects as appropriate to get
it to happen you can get a measure of
how effective your fault recovery
techniques are going to be
this is a results in the ability to
compute the measure for coverage which
is the conditional probability that the
system will recover automatically from a
fault that is detected you know given
that the fault is has been triggered and
activated and so you know verification
can play a role in that but it again
it's a system that really has stringent
availability and reliability
requirements that is going to go to that
extra effort of fault insertion testing
to verify and determine what the actual
coverage is although the specifications
might give you a coverage factor to meet
even if you can't spend the time to test
for it okay so then before we actually
look at the patterns and their structure
let's discuss a little bit about the
shared context for the patterns we
already talked about systems like
communication systems telecom systems or
flight control systems so I think one of
one aspect of the context is probably
the well the yeah obviously they're the
reliability and availability
requirements that are that are post
against the system what are the other
shared context items here well the in
the patterns that I've written about
they apply to both hard and soft
real-time systems or systems that aren't
real-time I think if you're designing
hard real-time systems you actually have
to go to a little bit further level than
I've described in these patterns so I'm
not saying that I put together a
complete pattern language in the for the
hard real-time case but there are a lot
of systems out there like even the
telephone network in many ways it's a
soft real-time system if you know
there's nothing catastrophic that
happens when a deadline is missed okay
we already talked about the the
availability aspect is there are other
things like statefulness or whatever
that was a problem that I ran into when
writing the book because a lot of the
patterns talk about state being
important or you want to save state to
allow recovery to happen faster
but some of them don't talk about that
and it really depends up on your design
space for the system you're building
whether it is stateful or stateless and
the patterns here really apply across
the board and there's some that are
really specific to state full systems
and others that aren't and so as you go
through and in your design you can't
look at every pattern and say oh yes I
must use this I must use this I must use
this you have to really you know be a
little intelligent and and I have a big
advocate that even if for example are
talking about statefulness right now
even if you're designing a system that
it doesn't have state that is persistent
or that is needed you might still get
some nuggets of inspiration about things
you should put in by looking at those
patterns but they may not all apply to
your case so anyway so kind of the
shared context the patterns it's a mixed
bag some talk about statefulness and
talk about statelessness you use them as
appropriate okay and I prepared that I
saw something called external observers
what does that mean right well many of
the systems in the world that are meant
to be fault tolerant are meant to be
left running unattended mm-hmm so like a
telephone switch there isn't someone
staring at every switch watching to make
sure that it isn't having a problem yeah
right now and so the systems are
designed for external observers you know
people or other either people or other
computer systems somewhere else that are
watching and monitoring their behavior
and those systems you know they might be
talking one of the standard protocols
like SNMP to put a name on one um but
these are these systems are interested
in reports you know oh error was
detected you know they're interested in
that because they might be doing some
trend analysis to detect whether there's
something that's a bigger problem than
the individual system is able to
determine or maybe it's a network-wide
problem and so there's an external
observer and so that's kind of
as you pointed out an underlying
assumption throughout this that there
are people or systems that are
interested in how well you know an
individual target system is behaving but
although we have these external
observers we still expect that the fault
tolerance is whatever that means we'll
discuss it in a moment is handled by the
system itself so the fault tolerance is
somehow integrated into the system yes
it's integrated into the fault RS is
integrated into the system because the
length of the outage or the length of
the failure the duration of the failure
will increase greatly even you know as
you start adding in communication
latency x' or this getting this the
other system to realize that it's a
problem and so you want the system you
want the time from the detection to the
resumption of normal operation to be as
short as possible mm-hm and so in order
to do that you put it on to the system
itself
mm-hm do we need to mention the other
things like long lived systems is that
is that important here well I'll just
say about about long live system which
is another item that because you do have
to spend a little extra effort designing
a system to be fault tolerant you
probably want it to last a little longer
than that system that you you know
tacked together over a weekend yeah so
yeah sure okay so that's I guess look at
some of the patterns in in the book and
basically let's look at how the book is
structured it's structured into several
chapters which is relate to certain
phases in building in a fault-tolerant
system do you want to elaborate on what
these five phases are before we then
look into the patterns that are useful
in each of these phases yes sure that's
a good idea
so I'm going to start with this
explanation of the second one actually I
just mentioned about how you want to
detect
that there's an error or a fault and get
it corrected quickly and so we've got it
there's a chapter
patterns to detect errors and faults and
failures and then once you detect it you
want to recover from them and or you
want to process the error and then can
either be going in one direction which
is you know kind of grossly changing the
state of the system changing the program
counter you're going to resume execution
in some new place that's what I call
repair recovery and the other concept is
error mitigation where you can fix it
without going to a totally different
place so like you can correct the data
right where it is rather than having to
transfer somewhere else
mm-hmm so those are the three middle
parts before that I've put architectural
patterns because there are a number of
things that you really need to design
into the system to the lowest level you
know throughout the system so that you
know to set the good framework yeah or
the fault tolerance and so the
architectural patterns I covered those
first but I wanted to mention detection
the other one and then the last of the
five areas that that you mentioned is
fault treatment patterns and this is
where we start getting to some of the
quality and other aspects because these
patterns are helping you okay you've the
system has automatically recovered from
the problem it's resumed execution now
let's take a look at that fault that has
occurred and really treat it and get it
out of the system and there's some
patterns that are useful for that treat
the root cause instead of just coping
with the problem exactly yeah okay I
guess we should start with the
architectural patterns I guess and well
they're probably also more or less some
of the umbrella patterns that are then
or that then encapsulate some of the
more detailed patterns we'll talk about
later
so um I think the way we'll do this is
that I'll just mention the patterns
Union and you'll explain them okay so
let's start with units of mitigation
units of mitigation is is a really basic
pattern and it's the first one in the
book and I actually used the Alexander
style so this is pattern number one
and when you're designing a system to be
fault-tolerant you need to decide what
are the levels or what are the blocks
that you will suffer a failure in is it
the complete system like your complete
web server goes down or is it that you
can no longer access the backend in case
of a failure mm-hmm but the other parts
will continue operating so you need to
decide you know in its pattern number
one what are the units of mitigation you
know what is the scope of what it is
that you can fail things to and this
also defines the boundaries about where
you will contain the errors and failures
because error propagation is a really
big problem and so you know these the
units of mitigation also tell you what
the boundaries are that you're going to
contain things in quarantine things in
later mm-hmm it's like more or less
establishing firewalls between different
subnets if one is infected the other one
is not harmed exactly an example are
reliability requirements such that you
can only have one minute of you know
outage per year for example yeah and yet
it takes your system two minutes to
recover then having the whole system be
the unit of mitigation isn't going to
meet that requirement if you assume that
one you know one failure occurs in the
year so it's there's there's there's the
firewall aspect and then there's also
the time aspect factor in how long it
takes to do things and can you meet the
deadlines can you meet the requirements
given these boundaries that you've
established correcting audits is the
next one this is a pattern that was well
it's very important in the systems that
I've worked in in telecommunication
systems and the point of the pattern is
that you the system is continually
looking at the data and checking it in a
number of different ways to determine if
it's correct and if it's not correct
automatically correcting it and this had
was one that was pretty early in the in
the book in an earlier draft and then
after listening to the comments by Ralph
Johnson's U of I group as they reviewed
the manuscript I realized that two other
people not working in Telecom this might
be you know a really insightful pattern
so if this one became number two and
some of the ways that the data can be
checked is you can check the structural
properties like linked lists is it
correctly linked in both directions yeah
you know are the stack and Q pointers
within bounds another thing you can look
at is known correlations you know if
you've got data stored in different
places maybe I am different formats
different representations are they all
really the same still do they all have
the same relationship that you think
that they will mm-hm
you know in another way is just a simple
sanity check is the range within the
accepted range you know is the year yeah
appropriate oh yeah won't talk about
that more and then direct comparison
there's some data that in your system
that might be so important that you
store multiple copies of it and you can
directly compare them you know the the
golden master copy that you never change
and isn't in right protected memory for
example compare that with the working
copy so that that's more or less already
redundancy right
yes that's already introducing some
redundancy into the system redundancy
being the next pattern right and the
redundancy it builds upon the unit of
mitigation and tell lets you know that
there are some parts of the system where
you may want explicitly to have multiple
copies doing the same thing storing the
same information in the correcting audit
case or performing the same computation
in you know a computational setting but
so you've design in the redundancy and
redundancy helps make the system fault
tolerant because if you have a redundant
copy if you detect that there's an error
in one copy you can switch to the other
copy very quickly it makes that repair
time much shorter well yeah well
assuming both are always up-to-date if
we look at the enterprise
systems the problem is always if you
have a standby how do you how do you
supply it with the correct state so that
it can take over one once the master
copy fails that's a really good point
but but even if it is doesn't have the
latest sure system state it still is
going to be a little bit faster than
having to complete the diagnosis and and
then do the repair and then do the
restoring of state you can you know
diagnose it later and let's get the
system the next patterns recovery block
which to me sounds like if it was
related to the unit of mitigation is it
is it basically the same thing but now
discussing what you restart once
something fails it's very much like
redundancy and units of mitigation
therefore but recovery block is also one
of the techniques that's widely
discussed in the literature as a way to
perform software to provide software
redundancy so you you know I just talked
about redundancy and people might have
been thinking well that's fine for
hardware but how do I do that with
software and recovery blocks give you
some ideas for how to do that with
software and the idea is that you would
try executing one block of code and if
if the result met some acceptability
criteria then you would use it and if it
didn't meet that acceptability criteria
you would use a different block of code
so it's kind of a cross between
redundancy and version programming which
I mentioned before and a way to to
implement that so it's it's a refinement
of redundancy and units and mitigation
and give some guidance on how to do that
in a software setting and to tie it into
what people might already be familiar
basically you can think about it as if
you were using a C++ try catch blocks
you know it's adding in multiple tries
yeah if in the within the catch so if
the first try didn't work then you've
got another one and so on I think it
just recently saw something like that in
the tutorial on early
that I read I think there is something
like that where it automatically retries
something else if something fails or
something I don't know that was
somewhere else I forget it yeah well I'm
not that familiar with Erlang but I'm
not surprised because her line came out
of the telecommunications world and so
it doesn't surprise me that they would
try this and like I said this is
recovery blocks has been widely written
widely written about also okay the next
two patterns are minimized human
intervention and maximize human
participation how do these two go
together in one system
minimize human intervention is a really
important pattern I think in a
fault-tolerant system and again it gets
to that time for the repair mm-hmm
because once you detect the problem you
have to fix it to resume execution and
if if the only option is to put a popup
on the screen saying oh an error
occurred click OK to continue yeah that
takes a long time yeah and so it's a
it's a funny example everyone's seen
those vlogs you know those pop-ups and
the idea of a fault-tolerant system is
solve the problem automatically don't
rely on people to be there you know to
hit the ok button you know immediately
so try to solve the problems
automatically but having said that
sometimes people really do know best
because they can get the bigger picture
or they know that well that they already
tried that and it didn't work and so
maximize human participation is kind of
the flip side and it's saying I'll
provide the means for those experienced
or those knowledgeable people to
actually make useful contributions to
the recovery mm-hm
so on the one hand do it automatically
because the computers going to be faster
and on the other hand you know let the
expert inject suggestions in to help
direct how the recovery goes faster yeah
but but keep them out of the critical
path right keep them out of the critical
path yeah okay the next one is
maintenance interface that probably is
related to this external
other things so there is other systems
that are able to monitor your system yes
exactly what you said but also those
people that are we're going to allow
them to participate in a maximal way we
need them to get the information to help
too
yep and so the point of maintenance
enter the make the point of the
maintenance interface pattern is to
separate out the the maintenance chatter
or the error reporting and the error
recovery kind of messages separate that
out of the normal input output stream
onto a separate stream that can be
monitored for that purpose because if
it's in the regular stream then you know
that things are going to get lost or
they're gonna be so other so many other
messages that things will be detected
and this points to a pattern language
that Greg stimple and I wrote a couple
years ago and was published in plot d4
which has a number of patterns for
dealing with lots and lots of output
mm-hmm yeah because that's something
that you easily have if you have these
typical log files it's funny this
maintenance interface just reminded me
about aviation where there is a separate
frequency for for emergencies which is
always clear so you can always speak and
if somebody says something there it's
sure that somebody's is going to look at
it something the same thing you just
said don't make sure that the important
maintenance messages are not like hidden
in the clutter of the usual stuff
exactly exactly or many
telecommunication systems might have GUI
you know web-based or otherwise yeah
primary interfaces and they still have
an extra emergency Channel that's plain
old-fashioned you know rs-232 link yeah
yeah okay the next one is again related
to humans someone in charge what does
that mean
well it's related to humans in it isn't
okay and the point of someone in charge
is you know if a tree falls in the woods
and there's no one to hear it
you know did it make a sound well if the
recovery action is attempted and it
fails is someone gonna realize that and
start restart it
and so someone in charge is really
saying that for everything you do in
trying to keep the system fault-tolerant
you the designer should know what other
part of the system and it could be the
operating personnel what other part of
the system is going to be monitoring
that and making sure it happens and if
it doesn't happen
initiate escalation which is the next
pattern and so someone could be a person
or it could be another part of the
system mm-hmm okay um and it's it's
basically nominate some tasks of the
system to initiate and monitor for
completion all the actions that you take
and now there's a potential gotcha here
which is I'm not trying to say that you
should have some sort of god entity that
is going to take care of everything it
doesn't have to be on that level it's
just for everything that the system does
it should know who's in charge of that
action and who's interested in that you
already mentioned escalation as one way
of building a hierarchy of related
reduced threat resolution strategies I
guess so how does that work in and
specifically well it's just exactly what
you said for every action think about
and this goes to the fault Telenor
mindset also for every action that you
might contemplate to fix a particular
error that might occur okay if that
doesn't work what do you do next and
design that into the system design in
the escalation path so that the system
automatically knows well okay didn't
work to to restore this from a
checkpoint okay so that means we have to
restart the larger entity but so to
predefine that escalation path you know
during design time so that during
execution time the recovery can be as
fast as possible mm-hmm right yeah fall
table saw us the next one in this
chapter fault observer is that part of
the system that is receiving the error
reports and it's the interested party
that's you know hey tell me what's going
on and I'll pass that information off to
the external observers or to the other
parts of the system that are interested
so it's the part I again minimize human
intervention so these are all
interrelated minimize human intervention
is talking about limiting the input or
the output rather to the outside world
and to people and relying on them fault
observer is saying hey I'll take those
reports for you and then I'll make that
report up to the outside okay
you know and I'll also give it to the
logging functionality and so it's kind
of the central point for the information
going out and again this is related to
the the input-output pattern language
and plot before book mm-hmm okay we'll
put a link to that into the show notes I
guess you have a PDF somewhere online
maybe I'll look for that I will figure
it out okay and the last one of the
patterns in the architectural chapter is
software update probably useful to
replace buggy or faulty code exactly and
it's something that even you know
working in a telecommunications company
projects have gotten quite far into
their design without thinking about how
they're gonna update it but again
fault-tolerant systems are long-lived
and unless you put in the hooks that you
need to add in a new version in the
first version you're gonna have a great
difficulty doing it and so this pattern
is to remind you you need to think about
software update up front so we'll stop
here for this episode in ten days you'll
hear about detection patterns error
recovery patterns error medication
patterns and fault treatment patterns as
well as the discussion on how to decide
with those patterns and why Bob wrote
this book I hope you liked this episode
and you hope you're looking forward to
the next to the next episode on this
topic as much as I do
thanks for listening talk to you in 10
days
[Music]
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want to get
more information about software
engineering radio or if you want to give
us feedback please go to our website at
se - radio dot net you can also contact
the team at team at SC
- radio net although we prefer entries
in our comment system on the website so
other people can see what you think
Software Engineering radio wants to
thank Henning poly for the intro and
outro music as well as Lipson for
providing the bandwidth this episode of
se radio as well as all other episodes
is licensed under Creative Commons
license see the software engineering
radio website for details